Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/Eis3A2Ll9_E
原视频发布日期：20200921
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
字幕字体：更纱黑体SC
And today I want to talk about the massive solid rocket boosters
今天我想谈谈那些巨大的固体火箭助推器(SRB)
which were the backbone of the Space Shuttle and will continue to do so for the SLS.
它们是推动航天飞机的中坚力量 并将继续用于SLS
these were the largest and most powerful rocket propulsion systems ever used in flight
在(火箭)发射中 这是有史以来使用的(尺寸)最大且(推力)最强大的火箭推进系统
And they're getting even bigger for SLS.
而且 SLS的固体助推版本会比这更大
When I've talked about rocket propulsion systems in the past,
当我过去谈到火箭推进系统的时候
I've often focused on liquid fueled engines and their complex plumbing and high pressure pumps.
我经常会关注液体燃料发动机及其复杂的管道和高压泵
And sort of dismissed solid rocket motors as being relatively simple
而对固体火箭发动机却不屑一顾 认为它相对简单
because they don't really have any moving parts
因为它们并没有真正的活动部件
but of course that is far from the truth.
但是事实远非如此
These are incredibly high-tech items that were developed back in the 1970s
这些都是上世纪70年代开发的高科技项目 令人难以置信
and were continuously improved even before the Challenger accident,
并在挑战者号事故之前就在不断地改进
forced them to take a hard look at certain features of the booster.
而在事故之后 迫使开发人员认真审视助推器的某些功能
But we'll get to that later.
但我们稍后再谈这个问题
At launch, the boosters accounted for more than half the mass of the Space Shuttle stack.
在发射时 助推器占了航天飞机组合体一半以上的质量
Each booster was about 600 tons and the total Shuttle stack was about 2000 tons.
每个助推器重约为600吨 而航天飞机组合体的总重量约为2000吨
Each booster would generate about 1250 tons of thrust
每个助推器都会产生大约1250吨的推力
whereas the core would only generate about 600 tons.
而芯级(航天飞机轨道器)只产生600吨左右
So these boosters for the first two minutes of flight
所以这些助推器在飞行的前两分钟里
would provide about two-thirds of the thrust needed to get the vehicle up and moving.
将提供约三分之二的推力 使飞行器上升并移动
Even before that, the boosters were critical
即使在那之前 助推器也是至关重要的
because the entire structure was anchored to the launch pad through the boosters.
因为整个结构是通过助推器固定在发射台上的
There were eight massive bolts
有八个巨大的螺栓
that would hold the boosters down with frangible nuts that would be detonated at T-equal-zero.
将助推器固定在易碎的螺帽上 在发射倒计时为0时引爆
Simultaneously the igniter at the top of the booster would be triggered and the booster would start running
同时 助推器顶部的点火器将被触发 而助推器将开始运行
and it wouldn't stop running for the next two minutes no matter what.
并且在接下来的两分钟内一直运行 除非触发中止系统
The propellant was a hard rubbery substance made primarily of ammonium perchlorate
推进剂是一种坚硬的橡胶物质 主要由高氯酸铵制成
which covered about 70 percent of the mass.
约占质量的70%
There was about 16 percent aluminium powder
其中有大约16%的铝粉
which would provide most of the energy for the combustion.
这将为燃烧提供大部分能量
There would be a tiny amount of iron oxide to act as a catalyst
同时会有少量的氧化铁作为催化剂
and all this would be bound together by something called PBAN
而这一切都将被称为PBAN的东西粘合在一起
because saying polybutadiene acrylonitrile all the time is quite a mouthful.
不说全称因为聚丁二烯丙烯腈(PBAN)是很拗口的
This material would be mixed at a factory and then molded inside the solid rocket motors
这种材料会在工厂里混合 然后在固体火箭发动机里面成型
混合推进剂
浇注前部分段
and they would have a material around the outside with a hole down the entire length of the booster.
(混合的时候)会让材料凝固在助推器(内部)的外围一圈 使整个助推器中间都是洞
When the booster lit the combustion is happening on the internal surface of this
当助推器点火时 燃烧发生在这个洞的表面上
and the hot gases are escaping down this interior channel toward the nozzle at the far end.
而热气体就沿着这个内部通道 一路向下 往远端的喷嘴喷出
The boosters were originally manufactured by Thiokol.
助推器最初是由Thiokol制造的
The contract was awarded in the mid-1970s.
合同是在70年代中期签订的
Now they are based in Utah and they needed to move the boosters which were very large to Florida
现在他们的总部设在犹他州 需要将这些非常大的助推器转移到佛罗里达州
which meant the boosters weren't moved in a single piece.
这意味着助推器不是整体移动的
They were made of multiple pieces which were joined together in Florida.
助推器是分为许多块 运到佛罗里达州后 再将其连接在一起
So the main booster casings were constructed from cylinders of steel.
那么助推器的主外壳是由钢制圆柱体构成的
They would be 3.7 meters in diameter and about four and a half meters long
它们的直径为3.7米 长约4.5米
and about 12 millimeters thick made of a very high quality high strength Maraging steel.
厚度约12毫米 由非常优质的高强度马氏体时效钢制成
They would take eight of these sections
每个助推器包括八个这样的部分
and join them together in pairs using a factory joint which would be permanent.
而助推器分段两两连接在一起 并在工厂里就永久性地结合起来
And then it would fill each section with the material.
然后用固体燃料填满每个部分
喷管的机器制造
But there's a little more that goes on than just pouring the propellant in.
但除了把推进剂倒进去 还有更多的事情要做
First of all there is an insulating layer on the outside.
首先 外面有一个绝缘层
绝缘层制造
It's about four and a half centimeters thick
它大约有4.5厘米厚
and it's a like asbestos-filled rubber.
这种绝缘层类似于用石棉填充的橡胶
涂抹衬垫
That's what they used on the Space Shuttle
同样也用在航天飞机上
安装绝缘层
and this is of course isolates the interior of the booster from the steel.
当然这也是将助推器的内部与钢壳隔离开来
Stops it getting too hot.
阻止它变得太热
把上部模芯放在钢段中
Isolates it from vibration and electrical, your currents and things like that.
隔离它的振动和电气之类的东西
Now for the SLS, they are actually replacing this with a new material
对于SLS来说 他们实际上是在用一种新的材料来代替它
because asbestos has many problems.
因为石棉有很多问题
And that's one of the reasons why we've seen tests of the booster rockets that are going to be used on the SLS.
这也是会对SLS上使用的助推器进行测试的原因之一
Because they need to validate the new materials.
因为他们需要验证新的材料
There are some other insulating layers interior to that but they're pretty thin
在这个绝缘层内部还有一些其他比较薄的绝缘层
and then you have the bulk of the propellant.
接着就是大块的推进剂了
The propellant layer is just over a meter thick.
推进剂层有一米多厚
Although this vAries depending upon where you are in the booster
虽然这取决于你在助推器中的位置
because the thickness will help control the burn rate during the flight.
因为厚度将有助于控制飞行过程中的燃烧速度
But that means there's a fairly large wide section in the middle.
但这意味着中间有一个相当宽阔的区域
发动机分段浇注料抑制剂准备工作
Wide enough for somebody to crawl down if they were, you know, crazy.
宽阔到足以让人爬下来 如果有人这么疯狂的话
At both ends of each section, there is a layer of inhibitor material added.
在每个部分的两端 都有一层抑制材料
This is like an ablative heat shield that stops the propellant from burning on the ends.
这就像一个烧蚀性的热盾 阻止推进剂在两端燃烧
涂抹抑制剂
There's a gap between each segment and the booster
每段助推器之间都有一个间隙
and if hot gases flowed in there then you would have extra combustion there
如果热气流进那里 那里就会进行额外的燃烧
they don't want that.
设计人员不希望这样的事情发生
So they control it with a material that will essentially ablate away
所以他们用一种烧蚀性材料来进行控制
and control the combustion to only be along that interior channel.
使得燃烧只沿着助推器内部的通道进行
On the very front segment of the booster
在助推器的最前段
there is an 11 pointed star that is cast into the structure.
有一个11角星铸造结构
This will burn faster early on giving them a little boost at launch
这将使发射时的点火稍快一些
取出模芯
and then those veins will burn away and the combustion will slow down a little
随着这些纹理烧光 燃烧过程就会减缓
X光检查前部分段
which of course helps them by reducing the thrust
当然就是推力会减少
during the point of maximum aerodynamic pressure or MAX-Q.
(刚好)会发生在最大气动压力或MAX-Q期间
This section also includes the ignition system which is up at the very front of the booster.
位于助推器的最前面这一部分还包括点火系统
点火器安装
The way it works is it's essentially a very small rocket booster.
它的工作原理类似于一个非常小的火箭助推器
It's actually a multi-stage system where you have a pyrotechnic igniter
它实际上是一个包含化学点火剂的多级系统
which ignites a bigger charge which blows hot gas down the middle, starting the booster
它点燃了更大的装药 让热气从中间喷出并启动助推器
and this happens in a fraction of a second.
而这一切发生在极短的时间内
And since triggering this is the point of no return,
而由于助推器点火是不可逆的
there are many locks to make sure this doesn't happen by accident.
点火机制中有很多锁来确保其不被意外触发
There's actually a physical pin that has to be pulled out before the system can even be used.
实际上 在系统可以使用之前 必须拔出一个保险栓
That pin stops the hot gas channel from rotating into position.
这个保险栓可以阻止热气通道旋转到位
So if a stray electrical charge triggers this while they're setting things up,
所以 如果在总装火箭的时候 一个意外(零散)的电荷触发了这个点火系统
it can't actually start the booster.
它就不能启动助推器
Somebody a couple of days before the launch has to go into the nose cone of the boosters
在发射前几天 得要有人进入助推器的鼻锥
and essentially pull out this pin to make sure the boosters are armed and ready for flight.
就是来拔出这个保险栓 以确保助推器已经进入准备发射的就绪状态
In front of this, the booster also has most of the recovery hardware
在保险栓前面 还有大部分的回收设备
including the parachutes, separation rockets.
包括降落伞和分离火箭
It also includes a set of rate gyroscopes to detect booster motion.
它还包括一套速率陀螺仪 用于探测助推器的运动
These are independent from the gyroscopes on the Space Shuttle itself.
这些都是独立于航天飞机(轨道器)自身的陀螺仪的
And of course,
当然了
having separate readings from both of the boosters was critical in figuring out what happened to Challenger
从两个助推器上获得单独的读数 对于弄清挑战者号事故的原因是很关键的
since the rate gyroscopes from each booster
这是由于每个助推器的速率陀螺仪
started to show very different values seconds before the destruction.
在事故前几秒钟 开始出现非常大的区别
Now if you move to the aft end of the booster you of course have the nozzle.
那么 如果话题切换到助推器的后端 首先是喷嘴
Now the nozzle has to interface to the rest of the pressure casing
那么 喷嘴必须与承压钢壳相连接
but the nozzle also has to move.
但喷嘴也要移动
So the nozzle moves on a two axis pressure sealed joint
那么 喷嘴就被设计为能在双轴压力密封接头上进行移动
that can handle the 60 atmospheres of pressure and the thousands of degrees of temperature.
这种接头 可以承受60个大气压的压力和上千度的温度
And this bearing is made by having many layers of plates
而这种轴承是由许多层板子组成的
that are essentially sections of a spherical shell.
这些板子最终构成了一个接近球形的形状
So these are stacked on top of each other
那么 这些板子都是互相堆叠在一起的
and then they're joined together by a rubber like layer
并由橡胶类物质构成的夹层连接在一起
but it's of course a rubber that can handle the temperatures and pressures.
当然 这种物质可以承受特定的温度和压力
So each layer allows a small amount of lateral motion
那么 每一层都允许少量的横向运动
and overall the whole nozzle can gimbal by about 8 degrees.
总体上而言 整个喷嘴的摆动角度大概有8度
The nozzle is moved by two separate hydraulic actuators
喷嘴由两个独立的液压促动器移动
which are at 90 degrees to each other to provide a full range of motion.
彼此成90度 以提供全范围的运动
The hydraulic system is pressurized by two separate redundant hydraulic pressure units.
液压系统由两个独立的冗余液压部件加压
These are self-contained power units.
它们使用的是独立的动力部件
They have a hydrazine fuel supply
由肼燃料提供动力
which decomposes, drives a turbine and then that pressurizes the hydraulic system.
燃烧肼燃料 驱动涡轮机 然后给液压系统加压
So they can handle a failure of at least one of these.
那么 这个液压系统至少可以处理一个动力单元的故障
The nozzle also has a nozzle extension attached to the back of it
喷嘴的后面还连接着喷管延伸段
which of course improves the efficiency.
喷管延伸段当然可以提高效率
But just before the boosters land in the ocean, this is removed.
但在助推器降落到海里之前 喷管延伸段就被抛弃了
It's severed by like a pyrotechnic device
分离的装置使用的也是火工品
and you'll see that sometimes fall into the water separately from the main booster.
你有时会看到 喷管延伸段会与主助推器分开落入水中
So a lot of this hardware is contained inside another component called the aft skirt
那么很多设备都包含在另一个部件里 叫做后裙板
that will also include some of the avionics and it includes the aft separation motors
这也包括一些航空电子设备 以及后部分离发动机
which are used to push the um the booster away from the spacecraft.
这个发动机用于将助推器推离航天器
The aft propellant section also has some extra features not seen in the rest the other segments of the booster.
后部的推进分段还有一些在助推器其他部分看不到的额外特征
It has extra reinforcement rings
它有额外的加强环
because this booster is one of the places where it attaches to the external tank.
因为这里是助推器和外部储罐进行连接的位置之一
Running vertically up the side of the rocket you'll also see the electrical tunnel
从火箭的侧面垂直向上 你还会看到电气通道
which contains your cables
其中包含着电缆
that need to run the length of the booster to communicate between the front and the rear.
这条通道达到了助推器的长度 是为了让顶部和尾部的设备进行通信
But you'll also find the explosives for the flight termination system which runs down the side
但你也会发现在侧面延伸到下面的飞行中止系统的炸药
if they're going to terminate the flight of the booster
如果控制人员要中止助推器的飞行
then the charge splits the thing along its length
那么 炸药就会把它长度范围内的东西撕裂开
and that of course stops the thing flying as the single mass and reduces the combustion.
这当然会让助推器停止工作 并减少燃烧
Of course one time this flight termination system was actually used was on Challenger.
当然 这种飞行中止系统只有一次真正得到使用 就是挑战者号事故那次
After the breakup of the stack, the two boosters kept on going under their own power
在组合体解体之后 两个助推器在自己的动力下继续前进
and had to be destroyed in case they went somewhere where they shouldn't.
这样就必须将其销毁 以防止失控坠毁造成的安全问题
So let's talk about the joints.
那么我们来谈谈接头的问题
As I said, the booster on the Shuttle was made from four segments,
正如我所说 航天飞机的助推器是由四个部分组成的
and each segment was itself made from two separate sections of steel.
而每一节都是由两段独立的钢段构成的
Now the sections were all joined together by a clevis tang joint
现在 这些钢段都由一个U形锁扣连接在一起
and this is where on one side the steel would split into two and form a y-shape
这是指 一边的钢段会分裂成Y形
and on the other piece would slide into the gap
另一边的钢段则会滑进这个缝隙中
and then a pin would slide through.
接着再在这之中穿过一根钉
Now if you have this in a complete cylinder on the wall of a cylinder
那么 如果是完整的桶状的钢段
you have many pins that go all the way around.
就会打上这么一圈钉
Now mechanically this is a very secure joint but it isn't pressure sealed.
从机械上来说 这是一个非常稳定的连接 但气密性不足
So to stop the hot gases from the inside coming out,
那么要阻止里面的热气出来
on the interior side of the clevis there's a pair of O-rings that were added in the original design.
就需要U形锁扣的内侧加上一对O型环 这也是最初的设计
And these would cut or go around the entire circumference
这些环会切开或者说绕过整个圆周
and when the interior was pressurized,
并在内部加压时
these would get pushed into the gap and stop the gases leaking through.
O形环将被推入间隙 阻止气体泄漏
The O-rings have to have some flexibility because this is a mechanical system,
O形环必须有一定的灵活性 因为这是一个机械系统
and when those boosters are firing they are bending and flexing under the loads.
而当助推器点火的时候 钢壳在(航天飞机主发动机施加的侧向推力)负载下弯曲变形
During early part of launch, these boosters are sort of flapping back and forth
在发射的初期 这些助推器会来回摆动
like strings on a guitar, three or four times per second.
就像吉他上的琴弦 每秒三四次
So the factory joints were generally more secure
那么(像前面说的) 工厂里连接好的接头一般都比较牢固
because interior to those, there was a continuous layer of insulation and the liner.
因为在这些接头内部 还有连续的绝缘层和衬垫
But the field joints which were assembled when the booster was being put together on the pad,
但是在发射场才进行组装的助推器现场接头
those necessarily had a discontinuity in the insulating layer.
这些绝缘层必然有一个不连续的地方
So as they were assembled, they would put a putty around the outside
所以在组装的时候 他们会在外面涂上一层腻子
and that would push itself into the gaps.
用腻子来填充缝隙
But of course the gases were expected to push past this.
但当然 腻子并不能耐受燃烧产生的热气
The O-rings were still very much the primary protective system.
所以 在这种情况下 O型环仍然是主要的保护系统
So in the case of Challenger,
那么在挑战者号的情况下
it was very cold and those O-rings didn't respond fast enough to fill the gap.
当时天气很冷 那些O形环的反应不够快 无法填满缝隙
As the booster was oscillating, it would find one side would be under tension.
当助推器在摆动时 有一边会被拉紧
And as those joints were pulled under tension,
而随着那些接头被拉紧
one side would get peeled away just because of the shape of the mechanical coupling
由于机械结合装置的形状 有一边会被剥开
and that would pull those joints with the O-rings wider
这样就会把那些带O形环的接头拉得更宽
and then as it was compressed they would get pushed back together
然后 被压缩的时候 两段钢壳又会被推回到一起
but that of course in that moment you would let gas get by and it would start to erode the O-ring.
但就在那一刻 气体会通过 会开始侵蚀O型环
As Challenger was leaving the pad
当挑战者号离开发射台的时候
the cameras recorded puffs of smoke three or four times per second
摄像机记录到每秒三到四次的烟雾
consistent with the oscillations of those boosters.
与那些助推器的振荡一致
But this smoke actually stopped after a few seconds
但这股烟其实在几秒钟后就停止了
and you know Challenger might have safely made it to orbit if it hadn't been for another factor.
而如果不是另外一个因素的影响 挑战者号可能就会安全地入轨
About 37 seconds into flight, they started experience wind shear
大约在飞行37秒后 挑战者号开始经历风切变
and it was the strongest wind shear on any Shuttle flight
这是航天飞机飞行中最强的风切变
so the boosters are now having to correct for these aerodynamic forces.
那么助推器现在必须纠正这些气动力
They're working much harder.
助推器需要超负荷工作
And of course these forces that are being translated into these boosters causing those joints to flex again.
当然 这些力被转化到助推器上 导致这些接头再次弯曲
And at some point, the joint again starts to come loose and starts leaking
在某个时刻 接头又开始松动并漏气
and that's when we start to see the real erosion happen and the jet of flame start to shoot out.
这时我们开始看到真正的侵蚀发生了 火焰开始喷出
And that flame of course damaged the external tank,
这样的火焰当然也破坏了外部储罐
and it damaged the coupling to the external tank
并损坏了固体助推器和外部储罐之间的连接装置
and eventually tank starts leaking, the booster comes loose at the bottom,
最后外部储罐开始泄漏燃料 助推器底部开始松动
and the vehicle, it breaks up under aerodynamic stress.
而航天飞机轨道器(则因姿态的变化)在气动压力之下解体
So of course the Challenger investigation happens.
那么接下来就是挑战者号的调查了
Richard Feynman does his amazing pop science experiment.
Richard Feynman完成了他那惊人的科普实验
And a number of recommendations are made to fix these joints.
并提出了一些建议来修复这些接头
So first thing they did was in the forward side.
所以他们做的第一件事是在前部钢板的一侧
They add a new flap that stops the O-ring section from being pulled away as tension is applied.
增加了一个新的挡板 以阻止O形环部分被拉开
On that they add a third O-ring as well.
在这上面他们还增加了第三个O形环
The pins are lengthened and on the outside, they add a retainer ring to hold the pins in place.
钉子被加长 同时在外面增加了一个固定环来固定钉子
And to this, they also add a heater to make sure the O-rings never get too cold.
而在此基础上 还增加了一个加热器 以确保O型环总是不会太冷
And on the interior, they just redesign the insulation so that there's something called a j-slit.
而在内部 只是重新设计了绝缘材料 这样就有了所谓的J型缝隙
And this is a gap in the insulation layer at the back.
这就是绝缘层上的一个缝隙
And what it's designed to do is the hot gases will flow into this gap and push the slit apart.
它的设计目的是让热气流进这个缝隙 并把缝隙推开
And this will actually force a section of insulation across the gap
之后 一侧的绝缘层会被推向真正要密封的缝隙上
and therefore increase the seal hopefully.
于是希望这样能增加密封性
It'll act as like another pressure seal helping to protect the O-rings.
这就像另一个压力密封圈一样来保护O形环
So these changes were made
那么 在改进措施进行之后
and the boosters flew largely trouble free for the rest of the Shuttle program
在航天飞机服役的剩余时间里 其助推器基本上没有出现任何问题
and of course they're now being re-engineered for the SLS program.
当然 他们现在正在为SLS项目重新设计固体助推器
There's lots of subtle changes to materials.
材料有很多微妙的变化
The O-rings now handle low temperatures which means they don't have the heaters to keep them warm.
O形环现在可以处理低温 这意味着不需要加热器来保持温度
The insulating material no longer contains asbestos
绝缘材料中不再含有石棉
and the boosters are now five segments long providing for more thrust and a longer burn time.
而助推器延长到五段 可以提供更多的推力和更长的燃烧时间
They are still using steel casings though
尽管仍然使用钢壳
while many modern solid boosters have switched over to use composite or filament wound casings.
而很多现代固体助推器已经改用复合材料或(碳)纤维缠绕外壳
But the Space Shuttle actually looked at filament wound casings very early on.
但其实航天飞机很早就研究过纤维缠绕外壳
Back in the early days of the Space Shuttle
早在航天飞机的早期阶段
they really wanted to launch the Space Shuttle into polar orbits from Vandenberg.
那时 (美国空军)想把航天飞机从范登堡发射到极地轨道上
And because it wasn't launching eastwards, they needed to have a bit more performance.
因为这不是向东发射(可以借助地球自转初速) 所以需要更多的性能
So there was a program to develop these lighter boosters using modern composite materials.
那么有个项目是开发这些使用现代复合材料的轻型助推器
Unfortunately of course that program shut down when Challenger happened,
当然不幸地是 当挑战者号发生时 这个计划就被取消了
there were more pressing concerns and the Space Shuttle never launched from Vandenberg.
因为事故调查是更紧迫的问题 而航天飞机就再也没能从范登堡发射了
There was one other rocket that flew with this booster design
还有一枚火箭采用了这种助推器设计
that was the Ares I-X that flew back in 2009.
那是2009年发射过的战神1X
The constellation program of course was planning to use these to deliver cargo and crew to the space station.
当然 星座计划当时正打算用这些火箭向空间站运送货物和乘员
Back in the days when many people didn't trust outside contractors like SpaceX to do the same thing.
当年很多人都不相信像SpaceX这样的外部承包商能胜任同样的工作
To be honest the Ares I-X wasn't much of a launch vehicle.
说实话 战神1X并不算一个(轨道级)运载火箭
It was all boilerplate with the exception of the main booster and a single unit that provided roll control.
除了主助推器和一个提供滚动控制的部件外 其他都是样板
Everything else was a dummy.
其他的都是模型而已
The booster wasn't even a full five-segment booster that was supposed to be used on the real thing.
助推器甚至都不是(战神1火箭)正式版会使用的完整的五段式助推器
And it lifted off and showed that well a Shuttle booster can indeed lift lots of mass
它升空了 并证明航天飞机的助推器确实可以推动大质量物体
but it was a very expensive launch for not even a fully functioning launch vehicle.
但对于功能不齐全的运载火箭而言 这是一次非常昂贵的发射
And commercial vehicles are doing this so much cheaper these days.
而现在的商用运载火箭进行空间站运输的任务 就便宜多了
So these big dumb solid rocket boosters that propelled the Space Shuttle and will carry the SLS
所以 这些又大又笨的固体火箭助推器 曾经推动过航天飞机 以后将运送SLS
are by no means low tech items.
绝不是低科技含量的东西
By any means, they are very much the product of rocket science.
无论如何 固体火箭助推器都算是富含火箭科学的产品
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]